Okay, I decided that before I go further on with
slides, in particular talking about higher-order
functions on lists, it would probably be good to
make another whiteboard style video where I again,
briefly talk about the syntax of function definitions,
in particular anonymous functions, sections
that we could then pass on to those
other, higher-order functions on lists.
And because the notes I took inside
the slides in the previous video,
maybe they didn't work so nicely in all cases.
Also because of my technical problems,
so I'm back to this setup here.
And well, what I'm going to
tell is mainly repetition.
So, let's recall.
So, how do we usually write new functions here?
So, I introduce some function
that I want to use somewhere,
it's a function from Int to Int.
And usually, I would say something like
'newFunction' with some useful name.
And it takes an argument and
maybe it computes x plus x.
Okay?
Doesn't really matter what it computes.
Okay, so that's how so far
you have introduced functions.
Okay, what we can do now,
that is what I introduced as part of
the slides on lambda abstractions.
You could now have written with the
same signature above, but instead of
the definition line (this one equation),
we could also have written this equation.
Yes, using this lambda syntax. So,
the lambda would look like this.
But as you have seen on the slides, in
ASCII syntax, we use the backslash for
this, instead of the lambda symbol.
But when I write it down, I will sometimes
write the explicit Greek lambda for this.
So, that's why it's called
lambda expressions/abstractions.
So, we could have written this line
instead of the one before, right?
Okay, in a named function definition, and in the
same way, we could actually also just use the
right-hand side directly in some function call
where we otherwise would pass the 'newFunction'.
So, let's say we have
somewhere a function call 'f'.
And then it needs an argument, which is a
function from Int to Int, and we could have
passed a new function as an
argument to that other function 'f'.
Or we could also write 'f'.
And then instead of using this name, or even
introducing this name, you could directly
pass a lambda expression to this.
Okay, and the important thing here is that here, we
need these brackets around the lambda expression,
we don't need this here in
the definition line as above.
And if you pass it as an argument to some other
function, we usually have to use these parentheses.
Why?
Because, for example, there could
be another argument later on, right?
So, maybe 'f' takes more than one argument.
And then we need to know
basically what the scope is.
So, this introduces a
variable x, what's the scope?
Well, in a place like this, it's until the end
of the expression, end of the line, basically,
because that's the right hand
side of a function definition.
But for example, in an application like this,
we need to know how far this x stretches
to the right, the definition or the scope.
And it goes, in this case, until this
bracket is closed, which was opened here.
Okay, so that's why we can't
simply write this without these
two brackets. It wouldn't be unique or clear,
what we mean by this.
Okay, so that's the part
about lambda abstractions,
and how they are used, what their role is.
Then there were these comments about sections.
And maybe it's also useful to
simply show how these sections
correspond to anonymous functions
with lambda abstractions.
So, let me make another quick note.
So, we had some things like "smaller
than five" as a predicate, for example,
you could also have this or maybe something
like this: > 0.5. So, this would be
the section syntax because we apply this
binary operator to just one argument.
In this case, the one we see here.
Okay, and this is really equivalent to: …
Let me also write this now with brackets
inside a lambda abstraction.
And inside the lambda abstraction, this would be
the same as an anonymous function which takes
an argument and then computes x > 0.5. And
if you use a section the other way around,
where we provide the left-hand side, the left
arguments…. So, if you had instead written
“0.5 >” and used this as our new function,
then this is equivalent to lambda x where 0.5
is greater than x. So, that's the rule of having
the sectioning to the left or to the right,
expressed as lambda abstractions, it's
clear, it becomes more clear maybe
we are the unknown or the
still-waited-for function argument
will go.
Okay, that's that.
And then also for later users, it's
interesting or important and relevant to know
that, of course, now that we have functions
as first-class values, we can also operate
on them in the way that mathematics allows
to operate on functions extensionally.
Not by looking inside the syntax, or the function
definition of a function argument used in a function.
So, we don't somehow get to look into how this is
defined, and then make case distinctions on this.
That's not something that we can do.
But operations that work semantically on
functions in mathematics can also be used here.
And the most well-known, I think,
is function composition, right?
So, if in mathematics, you have functions,
and the domain and co-domain of two functions
agree in a certain way, then you
can compose them. You should know
from your discrete mathematics course, for
example, or other math lectures in this notation.
If you have some function f and some function g,
then you can compose them and get a new function.
Yes, so if you have something like: g is a
function from the rationals to natural numbers,
and f is a function from natural numbers
to real numbers, for example, then you can
make from this: “function f compose g”,
which goes from the rationals to the reals,
because basically, a rational number comes in,
a natural number comes out, and then this,
via composition, is passed to the second
function, to f, and the outcome is a real number.
Okay, that's a typical operation
on functions in mathematics.
And well, the same is possible in
Haskell, of course, we don't use this
strange or funny circle here,
we need some other syntax.
And actually, we also need to
think about these domain sets.
And of course, the function
is polymorphic, right?
I simply use the rationals, naturals, and real
numbers here, for the sake of an example.
But essentially, we need to have
sets that agree in the middle.
Right?
So, what we have in Haskell
is the following operator.
It's just written as a dot.
Okay, as an operator, so again, in
these brackets. And what's its type?
Well, it's very polymorphic.
So, it has some type variables b and c
and the function between those types.
And there must be another
function that goes from a to b.
And the important part here is that
these two are the same type variable that
corresponds to the fact that in mathematics,
we need agreement on these two sets here.
And then what's the outcome?
Well, the outcome is, again, a function, but a
function from a to c. And how is it defined?
Well, given an f, given a
g, how can we define this?
Well, we can say, this is actually a
lambda abstraction, which takes an a,
passes it to 'g', where 'g' is basically a function
of this type, so we can give it an (a) value.
I have used the same term variable as the
type variable here. That's, of course, not
forced, but I just did it like that.
If I apply 'g' to something
of type (a), I get a (b),
and (b) is something of type (b). It is something I
can pass into the other function, the function 'f'.
Okay, so what I get here is 'f' of 'g' of 'a',
which is exactly intuitively the mathematical
notion of function composition, and now it's
available as an operator in Haskell as well.